Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, גוט חודש, gut chodesh, today's דף daf
is דף מ"א, daf mem aleph, 41. We pick up בבא בתרא
Bava Batra 41, we pick up with the משנה, mishna, two lines
from the top. And we are continuing of course the discussion of
חזקה. chazaka. And finally we get to this משנה mishna which makes
a point that we have established from the very beginning of the
פרק: perek: כל חזקה שאינה עמה טענה אינה חזקה. kol chazaka she'eino
imah ta'ana eino chazaka. Any חזקה chazaka that does not come with
a טענה ta'ana is not a valid חזקה. chazaka. חזקה chazaka does
not mean that because you've been in a place for three years
you have de facto, you have
like automatically somehow that entitles you to the right of usage. It's
not squatter's rights. It's used to change some of the dynamics within
the legal case, to give you a חזקה, chazaka, to make you
presumed to be the possessor of it, to be an explanation why
you do not have a שטר shtar to produce, to use evidence
about the fact that the person did not make a מחאה, michaa,
but it is not intrinsically something that gives you rights to the
place. And that's the point being made by this משנה. mishna. Okay
כיצד, keitzad, how is this the case? אמר לו, omar lo, אמר
לו, omar lo, the original owner, the person who is known as
the original owner says to you: מה אתה עושה בתוך שלי? mah
ata oseh betoch sheli? What have you been doing in the last
three
years dwelling in my house, reaping my, using my land, growing things
and so on? והוא אומר לו: vehu omer lo: שלא אמר לי
אדם דבר מעולם. shelo omar li adam davar me'olam. Nobody ever told
me not to. So אינה חזקה. eina chazaka. So okay, you're not
making any claim that you are rightful ownership; you just want your
three years to give you ownership; that it can't do. Fine.
So that is critically important to understanding what חזקה chazaka is and
what it isn't, and this was the understanding we've been operating in
from the beginning of the מסכת. masechet. שמא, shema, now if he
says however: שמכרת לי, shemacharta li, ושנתת לי במתנה, veshenatata li bamatana,
I am making a claim to ownership. You sold it to me,
you gifted it to me. אביך מכרה לי, avicha machra li, אביך
נתנה לי במתנה. avicha natna li bamatana. Your father sold it to
me, your father gave it to me as a gift. So הרי
זו חזקה. harei zo chazaka. That is a good חזקה. chazaka. Now
obviously there's a gap between these; the most obvious gap being suggested
here is your father gave it to me. It's a so fine,
he's still saying he has firsthand knowledge why he owns it because
he got it from this original guy's father.
But what if he doesn't have firsthand knowledge? Okay, which is the
final case in the משנה. mishna.
והבא משום ירושה אינו צריך טענה. ve'haba mishum yerusha eino tzarich ta'ana.
So if he however says not your father sold it to me,
I got it from my father, then you do not need a
claim, meaning the implicit claim is my father owned it, I presume
my father owned it, he was and I am an heir. Alright,
so even though I am not claiming direct knowledge of how my
father got it from you, and everybody knows that originally you were
the owner, for the last you know bit of while I've seen
my father on the land, he died, I inherited it, that does
not need a claim of direct, of direct knowledge. Now what you're
seeing is sort of the gray space in this משנה mishna is
about other scenarios in which you know you go from, there's like
two extremes. One is I'm not making any claim, I want my
חזקה chazaka to give me rights. The other is I'm making a
very firm claim, I know all the facts, I bought it from
you, my חזקה chazaka is evidence you're מוחה, mocheh, I didn't pay
attention, you know I didn't bother hanging onto my שטר shtar and
so on. What about all the cases in the middle where I'm
making a claim
but I don't have enough evidence to prove it? Cases like,
or not enough evidence, I'm not making a direct enough claim about
my knowledge to the case. Cases like I got it from my
father. I don't know where my father got it. And of course
the case that the גמרא's Gemara been dealing with, which we'll see
again here, is you know ראובן Reuven is the original owner and
I say I bought it from שמעון, Shimon, I assumed he was
the owner. A lot of cases where there is a טענה, ta'ana,
but the question is what constitutes a legitimate טענה? ta'ana? So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
פשיטא, pshita, says the גמרא. Gemara. This is obvious. It's only obvious
if we've been learning from the beginning of the פרק; perek; maybe
I would have thought that חזקה chazaka is like squatter's rights to
abandoned property. But okay, by now it's obvious. No, מהו דתימא, mahu
d'teima, I might have thought האי גברא מזבן זבנה ליה האי ארעא.
hai gavra mizban zabneilei hai ara. Maybe yes, we do understand that
a חזקה chazaka means it's being brought as evidence, it's being brought
in a court case that's based on claims. Okay, but I might
think that when the guy says nobody told me anything, maybe that's
not his real claim. Maybe that's not really why he should be
entitled to it. Maybe what really happened was that he bought it
from ראובן, Reuven, ושטרא הוה ליה ואיכס veshtara hava lei ve'irkas and
he had a שטר shtar and it got lost like normally what
a חזקה chazaka is coming to do, to be a replacement for
that or a reason why there's no שטר. shtar. והאי דקאמר הכי,
ve'hai dikamar hachi, and why is he saying I'm here because nobody
ever told me anything? סבר, savar, he assumes, אי אמינא מזבן זבנה
לי האי ארעא אמרי לי אחוי שטרך. ee amina mizban zabni hai
ara amri achvi shtarch. If the guy says I bought the land,
this guy doesn't know הלכה, halacha, the guy on the property, so
if he says I bought the land... If I make the the
right claim I bought it from you, then it's going to come
to court, they're going to ask me for evidence, I'm not going
to have a שטר, shtar, so I'm going to lose the case.
And he has no idea that חזקה chazakah would be a good
explanation of why he doesn't have a שטר. shtar. All he knows
is he's going to be asked to prove how this we should
why we should assume that this land is his, and he feels
I won't have that evidence. So therefore what will I do? הלכך
לימא ליה, Hilkach leima lei, you know what I'll do I'll say
to him, הלכך לימא ליה אנן, Hilkach leima lei anan, so that
that's why...
so this guy thinks, you know I won't win if I tell
the truth, so instead I'll just say nobody ever told me not
to be here and maybe, you know, that is a claim that
can win for all I know there is such a thing as
squatters' rights, better than the claim that I know I'm going to
be asked to produce documentation and not be able to do so.
So maybe that's really what's going on. And therefore maybe we should
help uncover that. הלכך לימא ליה אנן, Hilkach leima lei anan, let
us say to him, דילמא שטר הוה לך וחבשתיה, dilma shtar hava
lach vechavastaia, maybe maybe you had a שטר shtar and lost it
and maybe that's what's really happening.
You know, now of course there's a way you could ask that
question with genuinely trying to figure out whether it's true, or it
could be a very leading question: is it perhaps the case that...
anyway, כגון זה פתח פיך לאלם הוא, kegon ze p'tach picha l'ilem
hu, and maybe this would be the fulfilling of the verse open
up your mouth to the one who is who cannot speak, meaning
not everybody understands how you know to present their case in court
and we did not they didn't have lawyers. So obviously it's very
tricky because it could be a leading question but it's also could
be a way to get to the truth. So I might think
that that even if somebody does not have a טענה ta'ana we
should explore the possibility that there's actually is a legitimate
claim. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that we don't do that, that obviously
that could lead to, you know, a perversion of justice rather than
justice. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara never says it was an actual
הוה אמינא hava amina of the idea of squatters' rights, it took
it for granted that that could never be the case, it always
has to play a role within a judicial proceeding and as part
of backing a claim, but the משנה Mishnah is just making it
clear that even if that if the guy doesn't come with a
טענה ta'ana we don't try to explore the possibility of one. Okay,
now we're going to take a look at the application of this
משנה Mishnah and what actually does constitute a claim or not. רבנא
שקיל בדקא בארעיה. Ravana shakil bidka be'arei. So רבנא Ravana had a
there was a a a flooding in his land, and
it washed away the fence or the the wall between his land
and his neighbor's land. And what's going to be and then he
went ahead, אזל הדר גודא בארעא דחבריה, azal hadar guda be'ara dechavrei,
and he went ahead and he rebuilt the wall, but this time
he didn't rebuild it on his side of the property line, he
built it on his neighbor's side of the property line. So it's
going to be we'll see at the end that this was an
honest mistake, you know, he tried to rebuild the wall but he
actually built it a little bit into his neighbor's his neighbor's land.
So effectively now he has been building a wall and using his
neighbor's land, the land that is the wall is on top of,
does that give him a חזקה? chazakah? So let's take a look
what happens. אתא לקמיה דרב נחמן, ata lekamei deRav Nachman, he came
to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, אמר ליה, amar lei, so רב נחמן
Rav Nachman said to him, זיל הדר, zil hadar, give it back
to him. Okay, so then he said, והא אחזיקי לי, veha achziki
li, because it became clear that that was not originally, you know,
his land. So then he said, והא אחזיקי לי, veha achziki li,
but one minute, I have a חזקה, chazakah, I've been using the
land. Doesn't that show that I'm the rightful owner or doesn't that
give me rights to it as you're seeing this is a חזקה
שאינה מכח טענה chazakah she'eina mikach ta'ana it would seem to be?
So before focusing on the fact that there's no טענה, ta'ana, which
could be the obvious thing to focus on, he says back to
him, אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, כמאן כרבי יהודה
ורבי ישמעאל דאמרי כל בפניו לאלתר הוי חזקה? keman k'Rabbi Yehuda veRabbi
Yishmael de'amri kol befaniav lealtar havei chazakah? So now it becomes clear
that he was not using this land, he didn't build a wall
and didn't stay that way for three years. Very soon after he
built the fence/wall, the neighbor came and said, hey what are you
doing on my land, you know, so he so he so the
first pushback before we get to the טענה ta'ana is that is
this even a חזקה chazakah of three years? Now we do know
of opinions that say you don't need a חזקה chazakah of three
years.
One is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, right? We had רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda in the previous משנה Mishnah that said that the purpose of
three years is if somebody is in Spain, you know, you'll you'll
do חזקה chazakah for a year, it'll take a year to get
there, take a year to get the word back. But ultimately that
showed that as the גמרא Gemara pointed out that if the חזקה
chazakah was directly in front of the person, it would immediately be
a חזקה chazakah because if you needed three years, the message of
three years to get to Spain is going to take four years,
five years. So from that we inferred that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
held that a חזקה chazakah done in the presence of the original
owner immediately was a חזקה. chazakah. And רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
and what was רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? So we're going to see
that later on about a case of somebody who opened up windows.
windows, you know, created new windows in his wall overseeing his friend's
property, and you're not supposed to be allowed and you're not allowed
to do that because of היזק ראיה, hezek re'iyah, you're invading your
friend's privacy if there weren't windows there before, and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael basically says that if you went ahead and did it and
the friend didn't protest, then that then that's a חזקה. chazakah. That
gives you rights. Now, I that and that entitles you to continue
doing it. Now, I should point out, by the way, that that's
a very different type of a חזקה. chazakah. There you're not saying
I purchased the right from my friend to do that. That actually
is more along the lines of חזקה שאין עמה טענה. chazakah she'ein
imah ta'anah. By virtue of doing this and you not protesting, that
entitles me to the right of continuing to do it. Okay, so
we'll let's bracket that for a moment, but what we do get
from that is even immediately it's a חזקה. chazakah. So he says,
look, you didn't have three years. So he says, so do you
want to go are you claiming that immediate use gives you a
חזקה chazakah כל בפניו לאלתר הוי חזקה? kol be-fanav le'altar havei chazakah?
לית הלכתא כוותיה, leit hilcheta kevateih, we don't rule like them. So
that can't work. אמר ליה, amar leih, so he said to him,
והא אחיל? ve-ha achil? but what do you mean it? He was
מוחל. mochel. Now here becomes finally the טענה ta'anah which we did
not have before. Okay? He says actually I see from his actions
that I see from his actions that he actually was
okay. Like I'm not saying I bought the right or he formally
gave it to me as a gift, but his actions make it
clear that he was okay with me doing it. It was a
מחילה. mechilah. How exactly מחילה mechilah works on קרקע karka is an
interesting question, but okay. So, אמר ליה והא אחיל. amar leih ve-ha
achil. So that's the actual טענה ta'anah that that his actions show
that he was okay with it. How do we know that? דאתא
וסייע בגודא בהדאי? de-ata ve-sayei be-guda bahadai? that he came and he
helped me build the land. Okay? So now we have not only
the טענה ta'anah of the חזקה chazakah but we don't even have
really a חזקה chazakah of three years. Really what he's saying is,
you know, his actions are direct evidence that he has been okay
with this. It's sort of like some cases we had the other
day, right, when he sort of loads up the basket of fruit
and so on. All right? So so what what was the response
to that? אמר ליה, amar leih,
so he's back to him, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said back
to רב ענן, Rav Anan, מחילה
בטעות היא. mechilah be-ta'ut hi. It was accidental. Yes, he was he
helped you, but it wasn't that he was מוחל. mochel. Being מוחל
mochel means you know the circumstances and you're okay with them. This
was all under under, you know, mistaken assumptions. מחילה בטעות הוא. mechilah
be-ta'ut hu. את גופך אי הוה ידעת לא עבדת. at gufach i
havah yadat lo avdat.
So you yourself, if you had realized you were building the wall
on his land, you wouldn't have done it. All right? So so
now we finally understand, right? Because it was hard to understand the
case to begin with. Like why was רב ענן Rav Anan intentionally
enter no
encroaching on his friend's property? So now we find out the case.
The whole thing he thought he was building on his land, it
turns out that he was building on his friend's land, now the
friend is saying friend neighbor, now the neighbor is saying to him
you gotta knock down your wall, he obviously doesn't want to do
it, and he's saying well look the fact that you helped me
shows you're okay with it. And the response was he didn't the
your neighbor didn't understand that it was his land, you also didn't
understand it was your land, you don't now get the right to
be on it, you know, because of the mistakes that were made
in the past. כי היכי דאת
לא הות ידעת הוא נמי לא הוה ידע. ki heichi de-at lo
havat yadat hu nami lo havah yadei. The same way you didn't
know, he didn't know. So it was a מחילה בטעות. mechilah be-ta'ut.
Okay, so that's all of that makes a lot of sense. The
fascinating just part about this is that he did not bring in
the fact that there was no טענה ta'anah at the very beginning.
So the רשב"ם Rashbam tries to explain that there was a טענה,
ta'anah, תוספות Tosafot also tries to re-explain the case. It's hard to
exactly fit it in. But what's really fascinating is the גמרא Gemara
brings in this case in direct juxtaposition to our משנה mishnah and
not once was explicitly raised the problem that initially it seemed like
there was no טענה ta'anah and that and that only became the
טענה ta'anah only became came later on. All right. The other thing
worth noting is this point about about the חזקה chazakah of usage
when it's dealing with laws about הלכות שכנים, hilchot shechenim, which we
had before. You remember somebody will sort of put up an oven
and there'll be smoke and and the neighbor doesn't complain and there
it is a very interesting question. A, does that happen immediately? You
know, how long of a time do you need of lack of
complaining to say I've established my right to be doing this in
my land? I've establish to be having this oven, to be opening
these windows? And number two is how much do you actually need
a טענה ta'anah for that type of a חזקה? chazakah? Right, our
case משנה mishnah is talking about the classic חזקה chazakah of three
years, but the חזקה chazakah of like doing stuff in my own
property that's impacting my neighbor and my neighbor didn't complain, so that
gives me rights, how much does that need a טענה? ta'anah? If
you take a look at the רשב"ם Rashbam on the
משנה, mishnah, כל חזקה שאין עמה טענה אינה חזקה, kol chazakah she-ein
imah ta'anah einah chazakah, he says בין בחזקת ג' שנים דקרקעות ובתים
ואילנות bein be-chezkat gimmel shanim de-karka'ot u-vatim ve-ilanot בין בחזקת יום אחד
כהנך דאמרינן. bein be-chezkat yom echad ke-hanach de-amrinan. All right, so he
says that it really does apply across the board. We discussed that
earlier and we will discuss it again when it comes up in
a coming משנה mishna, *Mishnah*. All right, that was that case. Let's
take a look now at another case, a
parallel circumstances. רב כהנא Rav Kahana שקל בדקא בארעיה *Rav Kahana shakal
bidka be'arei*. So רב Rav כהנא *Rav Kahana* had land and he
had a wall, a fence in his land and came along a
flood and it wiped it away. אזל הדר גדרה בארעא דלא דידיה
*Azal hadar gadrah be'ara d'la dideih*. Exactly the same case. He rebuilt
the wall and we'll hope without fully understanding that this was that
he was doing it in his neighbor's property. He actually built it,
you know, within his neighbor's property. אתא לקמיה דרב יהודה Yehuda *Ata
lekamei de-Rav Yehuda*. This case came to front of רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda, *Rav Yehuda*. אזל אייתי תרי סהדי *Azal aiti terei sahadi*. So
now, so it, as opposed to the other case where he was
claiming I should be entitled to keep it, here once it became
clarified, he knew that he had to return, he had to, you
know, fix the situation and the question was where was the original
property line. So now we're on a different conversation, okay, trying to
establish where the original property line was so it could be rebuilt
in the right place.
So אזל אייתי תרי סהדי *Azal aiti terei sahadi*. So he went
and he brought two witnesses.
It's not exactly clear who's bringing the witnesses. Sound like רב Rav
כהנא *Rav Kahana* himself was bringing the witnesses, okay. You would have
expected that the neighbor was bringing the witnesses, but everybody presumably wanted
to do the right thing here. Okay. חד אמר תרתי אוציא עייל
*Chad amar tartei otzia ayeil*. One said he went into the neighbor's
property two furrow lengths. וחד אמר תלתא אוציא עייל *Ve-chad amar tlata
otzia ayeil*. And the other one said three furrow lengths. So do
we have any evidence now, you know, is it הלכתית *halachically* constitute
as עדות *eidus* in terms of where the line is? So אמר
ליה Amar leh, זיל שלים תרתי מגו תלת *Amar lei zil shalim
tartei migu tlat*. So רב Rav יהודה Yehuda *Rav Yehuda* said the
reasonable thing. Look, you know, they overlap as they both agree that
it was two furrow lengths. The question they disagree whether it was
the third furrow length as well. Clearly you have to put it,
you know, adjust it for two furrow lengths. Now he does say
זיל ושלים כפי *Zil u-shalim kefi* because it could be that he
did not want to knock down the whole wall and rebuild it,
so if I mean the neighbor could have insisted, but if the
neighbor was okay, then you could say fine, you could keep the
wall where it is, pay me for my land that you encroached
upon. All right, so that makes a lot of sense. אמר ליה
Amar leh, *Amar lei* so then רב Rav כהנא *Rav Kahana* though
said back אמר ליה כמאן כרבי שמעון Shimon, בן אלעזר *Amar lei
k'man k'Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar*? Who are you going like that says
that you can combine these two witnesses by saying that there's an
overlap of two and, you know, two and three at least agree
on
two? I read that wrong. אמר ליה כמאן *Amar lei k'man*. He
says who is this פסק *psak* following? So the response was, at
least this is how the רשב"ם *Rashbam* reads this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, *Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar*.
רב Rav יהודה *Rav Yehuda* said I'm following רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar *Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar*. Which רבי שמעון Shimon
בן אלעזר *Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar*? דתניא *Detanya* we taught in a
ברייתא *braisa*. אמר רבי שמעון Shimon. בן אלעזר *Amar Rebbi Shimon ben
Elazar*, לא נחלקו בית שמאי Beit Shammai ובית הלל על שתי כיתי
עדים *Lo necheleku Beis Shammai u-Beis Hillel al shetei kitei eidim* שאחת
אומרת מנה ואחת אומרת מאתיים *she-achas omeres maneh ve-achas omeres masayim* שיש
בכלל מאתיים מנה *she-yesh be-chelal masayim maneh*. Okay, so here you have
two sets of witnesses. Set number one made up of ראובן Reuven.
ושמעון *Reuven ve-Shimon* say that, you know, A borrowed from B a
hundred dollars. And then you have another כת *kat* made up of
לוי Levi. ויהודה *Levi ve-Yehuda* that says no, A borrowed from B
two hundred dollars. So does A at least owe B a hundred
dollars is the question. So and this was understood to be a
debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel ובית שמאי *Beis Hillel u-Beis Shammai*
or something in this area was a debate of בית הלל Beit
Hillel ובית שמאי *Beis Hillel u-Beis Shammai*. So רבי שמעון Shimon בן
אלעזר *Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar* says look in this case they both
agree that he owes a hundred dollars. יש בכלל מאתיים מנה *Yesh
be-chelal masayim maneh*, you might have heard that phrase before, it's a
common phrase. One hundred is included in two hundred. So everybody is
agreeing that a hundred dollars was borrowed. Now a way to understand
this is because one of these, you don't have to combine anything
here. One of these groups of witnesses is lying, mistaken
and one is telling the truth, one is accurate. So either way
you can take your pick which one you want to dismiss, okay,
but whichever one you dismiss you'll be left with at least a
hundred dollars of a debt. So even though we don't know which
one is telling the truth and maybe technically we can't formally accept
any one testimony, we do know that there's been testimony
that one way or the other there has been testimony that he
owes a hundred dollars. So he said in that case בית הלל
Beit Hillel ובית שמאי *Beis Hillel u-Beis Shammai* would agree.
So what did they debate about? על מה נחלקו *Al mah necheleku*?
What did they debate about? על כת אחת *Al kat achas* when
it's only one set of witnesses. שאחד אומר מנה ואחד אומר מאתיים
*She-echad omer maneh ve-echad omer masayim*. So ראובן Reuven *Reuven* says A
borrowed from B a hundred, and שמעון Shimon *Shimon* says no, A
borrowed from B two hundred. So now you can't just say take
your pick. Here you have to combine it and say well look
at this as one testimony on the facts that they agree upon.
We'll look at it as two people are both saying at the
same time. he borrowed a hundred dollars. בית שמאי Beit Shammai אומרים
נחלקו העדות. בית שמאי says, "Nope, sorry, you cannot combine them. They
are disagreeing, and I don't care
that factually it comes out that both of them are saying he
owes a hundred dollars, you need specific circumstances to be testified to
and you do not have two witnesses testifying to the same specific
circumstances." ובית הלל אומרים יש בכלל מאתיים מנה. U-Beit Hillel omrim yesh
be-khlal matayim maneh. בית הלל Beit Hillel. says, "No, we can be
more abstract,
and there's other cases like this where we can be more abstract.
Let's say one person says, 'A borrowed, I saw A borrow from
B a hundred dollars,' and another witness
says, 'I saw A
admit to B that he owes him a hundred dollars.' So can
you combine those? How much do you have to say they're testifying
to the same facts of what happened, or how much are they
testifying to the same sort of the legal implications of it? And
once you're a little more abstract about that, then you combine, at
least they both agree that he owes a hundred dollars. And that's
what בית הלל says." Okay, so that's exactly this case. One says
two, one says three, they're both agreeing that minimally you owe two,
that becomes testimony that you have to give back two. אמר
ליה, and so then רב Rav כהנא said to רב יהודה, ואמשינא
לך אגרתא ממערבא דאין הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר. v-amshina lakh igarta
mi-ma'arava d-ein halakha ke-Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. "I'll get you a letter
from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that the consensus is we don't פסקן
pasken like רבי שמעון Shimon בן אלעזר, and that even in this
case,
even בית הלל and בית שמאי argue in the earlier case about
two versus two, but when it comes to one versus one, everybody
agrees you cannot combine them." אמר ליה לכי תיתי.
Amar leh li-kh-tesei. "When you bring me that letter, I'll reassess
the case. But I don't believe it, I don't accept it, go
do that. Right now I am פסקנינג paskening like רבי שמעון Shimon
בן אלעזר according to בית הלל." And that actually is the הלכה
halakha that if one says a hundred and one says two hundred,
they combine to obligate the person as a hundred. And that's what
happened in this case. Nothing to do with our משנה, mishna. but
it was similar to the previous case of the flood washing away
the wall, which was a case of חזקה שיש עמה טענה, chazaka
she-yesh imah ta'anah, although that was not the focus of the halakhic
analysis of that case. Okay, ההוא גברא. hahu gavra. Now we're going
to get to finally real issues that really get to the key
line of the משנה. mishna ההוא גברא דדר בקשתא hahu gavra d-dar
be-kashta בעליתא be-illita ארבע שני. arba shani. There was
this guy that was living in this place קשתא Kashta in the
second story for four years. אתא מרי דביתא אשכחיה, ata mari de-veita
ashkachei, and the owner of the house came after four years and
found that this guy had been living in the attic. Who knows,
maybe he had rented out the bottom to somebody else or whatever
the case was, he certainly wasn't living in the bottom floor. Anyway,
he came and he found this guy had been living in this
attic for the last four years. אמר ליה מאי בעית בהאי ביתא?
Amar leh mai ba'it be-hai beita? "What are you doing in this
house?" אמר ליה מפלוני זבינתיה דזבנה מינך. Amar leh mi-flan z-vinteh de-zavneh
minakh. "I bought it from, let's say רעובן Reuven was the original
owner of the house, and he says I bought it from שמעון,
Shimon, שמעון Shimon told me that he bought it from you. All
right, and therefore I bought it from שמעון." Shimon, So it's not
only about the second story. Anyway, אתא לקמיה דרבי חייא. ata le-kamei
de-rabi chiya. This case came to רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. So is
this a טענה? ta'anah? He's not saying nobody ever told me not
to be here. He has a real claim: "I bought it from
שמעון Shimon who says he bought it from you." But the point
is,
do you know that שמעון Shimon, bought it from me? Did שמעון
Shimon have any evidence that he was the owner? It's like the
classic case of the Brooklyn Bridge. "Here, I'll sell you the Brooklyn
Bridge." How do you know that somebody who's claiming to be the
owner is the owner? Is that considered a טענה ta'anah because you
believed him to be the owner? But let's see if you had
any reason to believe him. אמר ליה, so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
said, אית לך סהדי דדר בה איהו דזבנה מינך ואפילו חד יומא
it lakh sahadi de-dar bah ihu de-zavneh minakh va-afillu chad yoma וקמיה
ליה בידך. u-kima leh be-yadekh. "If you have evidence that
שמעון Shimon was living in it for one day, and because he
was living in it for one day you presumed him to be
the owner, then that works. That becomes a חזקה שיש עמה טענה."
chazaka she-yesh imah ta'anah. So this is something we've been dealing with
earlier on, and this is fascinating
because you could understand both sides of why that should be a
טענה. ta'anah. The reason you should assume that it should be considered
valid is because if you say not, it's going to throw total
havoc. I'm going to buy a piece of property, and then the
person who owned it two steps back is going to say, "What
are you doing with this piece of property?" I'm going to say
I bought it, and then they're going to say, "But I don't
know that direct evidence that he had directly bought it from you,"
and so on. So it could be highly disruptive to society if
I always had to be concerned about the claim, not just hold
on to my documentation that I bought it from שמעון, Shimon but
I had to be concerned that רעובן Reuven would come and challenge
the fact that שמעון Shimon actually owned it. On the other hand,
you could say why is that so terrible? Before you buy a
property, do a title search. Before you buy a property, demand from
the person you're buying it from to bring evidence that he's the
owner. So, we could sort of understand why, from a societal perspective,
we could make it work. Now, how about from the formal תנא
Tanna perspective? Well, on the one hand, you could say, you know,
why is this a good claim? We will totally believe you if
the idea of the חזקה Chazakah is, and this might go back
to the original question of what the idea of the חזקה Chazakah
is. If the idea of the חזקה Chazakah is that, you know,
your, it's because I didn't hear anything from you I wasn't careful
for my שטר, Shtar, but you should believe me that I had
a שטר. Shtar. So then it's like, okay fine, we believe you
that you had a שטר. Shtar. You had a שטר Shtar that
you bought it from שמעון, Shimon but there's no, but שמעון Shimon
can't prove that he was the owner. So, you know, if we
put all the evidence on the case, you bought it from שמעון,
Shimon nobody's contesting that, but שמעון Shimon can't prove he's the owner,
give me back my land. And that would be a case why
that should not work, unless שמעון Shimon was there for three years,
then שמעון Shimon also can presume, you know, there's presumption that he's
the owner. On the other hand,
if it's less that like I lost my שטר Shtar and like
your silence is evidence that you were okay with this situation, but
we still have a reality that you were silent for three years,
and if I didn't have a right to be living in it,
and if שמעון Shimon's wasn't the owner, then you should have said
something. Right? So you could sort of understand, you know, going that
way. Also, if what a חזקה Chazakah is, is it makes me
considered the מוחזק, Muchzak, and then the burden of proof shifts from
the original, from being on me to being on the original owner,
so, you know, now the burden of proof is back on ראובן.
Reuven, So there's different ways in which you could understand why this
should be good. On the one hand, even if I'm totally telling
the truth, it doesn't prove that שמעון Shimon purchased it. On the
other hand,
maybe your silence proves that the situation is an okay situation and
maybe at least I'm a מוחזק Muchzak and that puts the burden
of proof on you. All right, so the way that רבי חייא
Rebbi Chiya responded to this was he said that if you can
prove that שמעון Shimon was on it for one day, then that
creates a legitimate טענה. Ta'anah. Okay, then it's not just, then at
least that somewhat establishes the legitimacy of your claim, and then it
creates a legitimate טענה. Ta'anah. יצחק בר אדי דזבנה מינך ואפילו חד
יומא אוקימנא לה בידך ואי לא לא. Yitzchak bar Addi de-zavnah minach
va-afillu chad yoma okimnah lah beyadach ve-ee lo lo. So we'll keep
it in your
hand and if not, not. אמר רב הוה יתיבנא קמיה דחביבי, Amar
Rav hava yasvina kamei de-chavivi,
I was sitting in front of my beloved one, which is רבי
חייא, Rebbi Chiya, who was his uncle. ואמרי ליה, Ve-amri lei, and
I said to him, וכי אין אדם עשוי ליקח ולמכור בלילה? Ve-chi
ein adam asui likach velimkor balaylah? So I don't get it, why
does it have to be one day?
Maybe שמעון Shimon did a very quick turnaround, he bought it from
ראובן Reuven, at night and turned around and sold it to this
guy at night and he wasn't even in it for a full
day. So it's a question like, does he mean to say that
you should not, maybe you don't need any evidence of even one
day? That's just considered a טענה. Ta'anah. I'm claiming that I'm the
rightful owner and I was in it for three years and you
didn't protest. Okay, and maybe I don't know that שמעון Shimon really
did it, but you also didn't protest. So he says, you know,
it could happen that he wasn't even in it for one day.
וחזיא לדעתיה, Ve-chazya le-da-ateih, and I saw that his, when he was
answering me, I saw that his intention, his הלכה halachic opinion was
the following: אי אמר ליה קמי דידי זבנה מינך מהימן. Ee amar
lei kamei didi zavnah minach meheman.
If the person who's in the land says to ראובן, Reuven I
saw שמעון Shimon buy it from you, I have direct knowledge, then
that's a טענה. Ta'anah. You don't need any evidence that שמעון Shimon's
was in the land. Then he's just directly saying, I have direct
knowledge that this, you know,
that this property
was yours and then it was שמעון Shimon and then I bought
it from him. And if you believe me because of my חזקה
Chazakah that I lost my
שטר, Shtar, then that should be believed. מיגו דאי בעי אמר ליה
אנא זבנתה מינך. Migo de-ee ba'ei amar lei ana zavnita minach. The
same way I'd be believed to say that I bought it from
you, from ראובן, Reuven. and the fact that I don't have a
שטר Shtar is not a problem, I've been here three years and
you should have said something, I can also say another definite claim:
I bought it from שמעון Shimon who I saw bought it from
you. So he's saying, I don't say you always need שמעון Shimon
to be there on the, you know, for a day, but you
do need one or the other. You do need to either, you
know, have a direct claim that you know that שמעון Shimon. was
the owner, or if you can't do that, then you have to
prove that שמעון Shimon was there for a day. Okay, and the,
there you could go, you know, what רב thought the הלכה Halacha
would be, maybe שמעון Shimon. has to be there for three years,
maybe I have to see שמעון Shimon שטר, Shtar, maybe I need
direct evidence. Or you go the other way, even if שמעון Shimon
wasn't there for a day and I can't prove it, maybe he
was but I can't prove it, nevertheless I've been on this land
and I'm claiming I'm the rightful owner and you should have said
something. Okay, so. So, but in the end we פוסקין *pasken* that
you need one day evidence or to be able to claim you
have direct knowledge that שמעון Shimon *Shimon* was the owner. אמר
רבא *Amar Rava*, said רבא *Rava*, כוותיה דרבי חייא מסתברא *kevasei deRabbi
Chiya mistavra*, according to רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiya* it makes sense, דתני
הבא משום ירושה אינו צריך טענה ta'ana. *detani haba mishum yerusha eino
tzarich tana*. Let's look at a similar case in our משנה mishna
*mishna*. Somebody that inherits land doesn't need a טענה ta'ana, *tana*. Now,
if he can't prove that his father bought it from ראובן Reuven
*Reuven*, if in this case his father is שמעון Shimon, *Shimon*, and
he can't prove that his father bought it from ראובן Reuven *Reuven*,
then we're back to the same case. We believe that you got
it from your father, your father died and you've been on it
for three years, but I ראובן Reuven *Reuven* have evidence that I
was the original owner and you can't prove that your father bought
it from me. Now obviously, what kids are supposed to know exactly
where their parents get all their property from? But let's take a
look. טענה ta'ana, הוא דלא בעי הא ראיה בעי *Tana hu delo
bei ha raya bei*. So this is of course a very creative
read of the משנה mishna. *mishna*. I don't have to prove, I
don't have to have a claim that I know my father bought
it from you, but I do need to bring some evidence to
establish
his presence on that property, which is reading that in the משנה
*mishna* is bizarre, because the משנה *mishna* makes it sound like all
you need is a חזקה hazaka, *chazaka*. And now we're saying you
don't need a טענה *tana*, but you would need something to represent
the evidence of where you got it from. So you do need
to establish that your father was on that property at least for
one day. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, who says that's the
reading of the משנה *mishna*? ודילמא לא ראיה בעי ולא טענה בעי
*udilma lo raya bei velo tana bei*. So he says, first of
all, I don't buy it. Who says that's the reading of the
משנה *mishna*? Could be a יורש yoresh *yoresh* doesn't need proof or
any evidence. He inherited it, he's been here three years, he says
he got it from his father. Again, you could understand that that
can work even without
a טענה *tana*, when there's a person that's the intermediate person that
you're getting it from. So number one is that could allow for
the idea that you don't need any ראיה *raya*. Number two, ואיבעית
אימא שאני לוקח דלא שדי זוזי בכדי *ve'iba'is eima shani lokei'ach delo
shadei zuzei bechidi*. A purchaser is different, which is like a buyer.
A buyer, there's the fact that I am claiming I bought it
from שמעון Shimon *Shimon* and I spent ten thousand dollars, a hundred
thousand dollars, and I bought it from שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, even if
I can't prove that שמעון Shimon *Shimon* has been there for a
day or for three years or whatever, we can presume that if
my חזקה hazaka. *chazaka* makes my טענה *tana* believable that I spent
the money and bought it from שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, then I would
have done enough research and I'm not saying I had no idea,
I looked into it, I this, I that, I just can't bring
the evidence to court to show that שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* is the
owner. In that case, that strengthens my טענה *tana* and that's a
legitimate טענה *tana*. Okay, so what we have here is a range
of possibilities. The guy says he bought it from שמעון Shimon
*Shimon*. ראובן Reuven *Reuven* claims שמעון Shimon. *Shimon* was not the rightful
owner. The guy now will say based on where the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* concluded is saying, look, I knew that שמעון Shimon. *Shimon* had
been living on it, nobody was saying anything, maybe I even asked
שמעון Shimon *Shimon* to show me the documentation, I saw the documentation,
no I do not have a copy of the documentation, or maybe
he didn't say that but I looked into it. Nothing that I
can prove, maybe nothing that's a hundred percent, but I looked into
it enough to satisfy
any doubts, and I bought it from שמעון Shimon *Shimon*. So is
that good enough? So you could say that doesn't need to prove
anything about שמעון *Shimon*, that's completely legitimate and
people would not spend their money without anything and maybe you don't
need to prove anything,
that is a good טענה *tana*.
Or you could
say
no, you need to at least a little bit establish that. So
you have to prove that שמעון *Shimon* was there for a day.
Or you could say maybe you need to totally
prove that שמעון *Shimon* was
there. Whole range of possibilities, different circumstances, but at the end we
are settling on that I need to either establish that the person
before me was there for a day, whether it's my father or
whether it's the guy I bought it from, or to say I
have direct knowledge, direct knowledge that it was his. Okay. איבעיא להו:
נירא בו מאי *Iba'ya lehu: nira bo mai*? When we say that
I have to prove that שמעון *Shimon* was there for a day,
does that, what if שמעון *Shimon* was on the property, he wasn't
living in the property, he wasn't working the land? Land, he was
scouting it out, he was measuring it, you know, acting like, you
know, maybe an owner would act, but not the classic usage. Okay,
so אמר אביי he, he, it's the same, that's enough to anchor
my טענה. רבא אמר Rava amar עבידי אינשי דסיירי ארעא ולא זבני.
Avidi inshi desairi ara velo zavni. No, people sometimes will, you know,
go ahead and they will scout out land, you know, and not
sell it, meaning that they, that
it's not their property, you know, maybe שמעון was scouting it out
and he was considering buying it. That doesn't give me, that doesn't
help establish the idea that שמעון was the owner. Okay, so we
have the idea that you need a טענה, that a יורש yoresh
does not. Presumably, the פשט pshat of the משנה is a יורש
yoresh doesn't have to prove anything because again, you could understand why
a חזקה, you know, why even like this case of I got
it from somebody else, he's claiming he's a rightful owner, and maybe
that's enough, or does he have to prove, you know, all the
various steps? So from the case of the משנה it sounds like
for a יורש you do not have to prove, but the גמרא
and then what's the case about somebody who purchases it from somebody
in the middle? And in the end, the גמרא seems to settle
on: you have to in both cases prove that the middle person
was there either for one day, that, that gives some sort of
way of anchoring your טענה, or to claim direct knowledge. Okay. Now
we're going on to another case of חזקה. שלשה לקוחות מצטרפין. Shlosha
lekuchot mitztarfin. And this is not really directly related to our משנה.
Three purchasers combine. ראובן Reuven was, worked land for one year and
then he sold it to שמעון. שמעון worked it for one year
and then he sold it to לוי. Levi And לוי Levi worked
it for a year. And then comes, you know, יהודה and says,
what, what are you guys doing on my land? Oh, well we
got it, so I got it from שמעון. שמעון says, I got
it from ראובן. Reuven And so what's ראובן Reuven going to say?
ראובן Reuven, can't prove, he doesn't have a שטר, shtar, and ראובן
Reuven hasn't been there for three years. So the question is: oh,
all three of us combined have been using it for three years
and you should have said something. And once I didn't see you
saying anything after, you know, consecutive owners were using it for a
duration of three years, I stopped being careful with my שטר. shtar.
All right, so, so maybe יהודה can say, I had no idea
that these were consecutive owners and you were claiming that one had
been sold to the next and to the next. I just thought
three different people. I don't have to do a מחאה mecha'a until
one person is using it for three years, so I had no
reason to respond.
אמר רב וכולם בשטר. Amar Rav vechulam beshtar. Ah, there has to
have been a שטר. shtar. ראובן Reuven. has to have sold it
to שמעון with a שטר, shtar, and שמעון has to have sold
it to לוי Levi. with a שטר. shtar. And now the claim
is like this: okay, you saw three different people, but also if
there was a שטר, shtar, people know, you know, that requires going
to בית דין, Beis Din, getting witnesses, not everybody was literate, it
was a production. So if you knew that I was selling it
to שמעון, you know, there was enough basis for you to find
out that I had sold it to שמעון because I wrote a
שטר shtar and that would have caused some publicity. And then you
had enough basis for you to hear that שמעון had sold it
to לוי. Levi, And you saw that combined we were all on
it for three years. If, if none of that was true and
I didn't originally own it, you needed to have made a מחאה.
mecha'a. למימרא, Lemimra, the גמרא says, דסבר רב שטר אית ליה קלא
ועדים לית ליה קלא? desavar Rav shtar is lei kala ve'eidim leis
lei kala? This sounds like רב is of the opinion that a,
only with a שטר shtar does, does there, is there a voice,
meaning only with a שטר shtar does the word get out? And
therefore, you as the original owner should have been מוחה mocheh because
we can be presumed that you knew that the three of us
are working in a chain. Okay, but if there was no שטר,
shtar, just witnesses that ראובן Reuven sold it to שמעון and שמעון
sold it to לוי, then we can't, we can't presume that you
as the original owner knew anything about it. So is this true
that רב says that only with a שטר shtar do things become
public but not with normal witnesses? ואמר רב המוכר שדהו בעדים גובה
מנכסים משועבדים? Va'amar Rav hamocher sadehu be'eidim goveh minechasim meshuabadim? But רב
says that if I sell, you know, my field with witnesses, then,
then, you know, the, the, you can go ahead and collect from...
then if the... you know, so, you know, I sold my field
to ראובן Reuven and let's say I sold my field to ראובן
Reuven with a שטר. shtar. And in the שטר shtar I say
if any creditors come and take it from you, I will be
responsible. Then comes a creditor who has liens and takes it from
ראובן, Reuven ראובן Reuven produces the שטר shtar and I have to
reimburse ראובן. Reuven. But if I did the same thing with ראובן
Reuven, but there was no שטר, shtar, there was just witnesses and
I said I accept responsibility if the creditors take it from you,
רב says that now some say that does not work because, you
know, the, because the people that are going to be... excuse me,
I left out one part, which is that: so I go ahead
and I sell it to ראובן Reuven and I say if creditors
take it from you you can I will I will be responsible.
Now that happened and... ראובן Reuven comes back to me to collect
it, and I don't have any money on me. Okay, so what
can ראובן Reuven do? ראובן Reuven can now collect my debt to
him from land I sold to שמעון, which I did after I
sold it to ראובן. Reuven That idea that I say to ראובן,
Reuven if creditors come and take it, then they have liens on
my property, I will reimburse it, so then I made that commitment
to ראובן Reuven or that legal obligation, that gave ראובן Reuven liens
on my property to collect that obligation. So now ראובן Reuven comes
back to me once the creditors took it from him, I don't
have the money, he can go to שמעון because he had liens
on the lands that then I sold after I sold the land
to ראובן Reuven that I sold to שמעון. So that's the principle
of
גובה מנכסים משועבדים. Gova MiNechasim Meshubadim. Now, what if when I sold
it to ראובן with this אחריות, achrayus, with this liability, this responsibility,
you know, if it gets taken by creditors, there was no שטר
shtar out, there was only witnesses to that? So there's some that
would say that ראובן cannot collect it from שמעון. Why not? Because
since it was only with witnesses,
you know, if somebody is going to take property that there are
liens on, we can only allow that, we can only be fair
to them if they have a way of finding out that there
are liens on the property. And that's why you need a שטר.
shtar. So if there was a שטר shtar out there that I
sold it, that I sold this land to ראובן and I accepted
אחריות, achrayus, then there were, people would know that now ראובן has
liens on all my property from the date of that שטר shtar
onwards, and it's, you know, buyer beware. And if שמעון buys my
property, he should be aware that there are liens. But if I
sold it to ראובן with witnesses, it's not enough public knowledge, and
therefore it does not give ראובן liens on my property if שמעון
is going to buy it. You know, much simpler case is just
lending money. If I lend you money with a שטר, shtar, I
get liens on your property. If I lend you money with witnesses,
I don't have liens on your property. Okay, that's the case by
lending money, but anyway, in the case of sale, רב says that
the presence of witnesses will be enough to make it public and
will create liens. So how is that different in our case? Why
is there an insistence on a שטר shtar if witnesses normally is
enough to make it public? הגמרא Gemara says התם לקוחות אינהו דאפסידו
אנפשייהו. Hatam Lakochot Inhu D'Apsidu Anafshaihu. No,
there's a difference between the lack of מחאה mecha and purchasers. You
know, in the case of purchasers, you are making a decision whether
to purchase this land or not purchase this land, and
as and and there you're actively going to research, you have a
responsibility to research if there are liens. So as long as there
are witnesses around,
that that information is out there to be found. And if you
didn't do your due diligence, then you don't get those liens. Okay,
so so that's that principle. And again, it might be different between
borrower and lender, but purchaser, you should be responsible to research whether
there are liens and the presence of witnesses is enough. By מחאה,
mecha, we need the information to get to the original owner. The
original owner isn't actively doing something and has to research it. Somebody
is on his property that he doesn't know about. Okay, so therefore
we need it enough naturally and organically to get to him, not
only something that is available through research. Okay, we'll stop here.